<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Aldrin User Manual</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Leonard</firstname>

        <surname>Ritter</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <date>02/04/2007</date>

    <releaseinfo>0.10</releaseinfo>

    <copyright>
      <year>2007</year>

      <holder>The Aldrin Development Team</holder>
    </copyright>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book describes usage and configuration of Aldrin, a powerful
      music composition software for the GNU/Linux operating system.</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Welcome to the Aldrin User Manual. In this book you are going to
    learn how to master Aldrin, a powerful music composition software for the
    GNU/Linux operating system. Its compact and integrated structure allows
    you to write electronic music without requiring expensive audio gear, but
    in case you have those already, they can be easily utilized as
    well.</para>

    <para>Aldrin features a flexible audio routing system commonly found in
    expensive audio software, enabling you to mix, split, mutilate and modify
    audio signals emitted by software synthesizers and samples. An
    ever-expanding number of included plugins ensures that you never run out
    of good sounds. The wavetable organizes your samples and sampler patches,
    enabling multiple instruments to share the same set of sounds. The classic
    tracker interface supports sequencing rhythms and melody patterns using
    your PC keyboard as a piano. Finally, a multitrack sequencer organizes
    your overall song structure, allowing you to arrange patterns along a
    vertical timeline.</para>

    <para>With Aldrin, you're no longer alone. Exchange songs with others,
    remix and extend unfinished works. Aldrin embeds easy access to Freesound,
	the online sample library for creative commons licensed sounds. Aldrins 
	CCM song format contains everything required to faithfully reproduce
	a composition on a different installation: patterns, sequences, sounds,
	effects, instruments, everything is preserved in a compact and extensible
	format.</para>

    <sect1 id="features">
      <title>Features</title>

      <para>Here is a list of some of Aldrins features to wet your appetite.
      It can never be complete, as Aldrin is constantly being extended and
      improved.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Utilizes the powerful libzzub player library for best
          performance and feature richness.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Playing-piano-like pattern editor with extensive keyboard
          command support.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Step sequencer with unlimited number of tracks per
          plugin.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Modular router supporting generator and effect plugins.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Plugin parameter editor with preset management and sliders to control individual
          parameters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sound library supporting import and export of FLAC, WAV, AIF and MP3 files.</para>
        </listitem>
		
		<listitem>
		  <para>Embedded interface to The Freesound Project. Allows to preview and download samples on the fly.</para>
		</listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Recording events sent from external MIDI gear and mouse cursor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Envelope editor for samples with ADSR generator and load/save
          support.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for CCM as default fileformat: XML song data, Flac
          samples and Lunar dsp scripts packed as zip archive.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Features the powerful Lunar DSP scripting engine.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for ALSA, Jack and OSS audio drivers.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All effects operate on stereo 32-bit floating point buffers
          for maximum quality.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Supports CD- and production-grade samplerates.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HD Recorder supports downmixing of songs to WAV for production
          use.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for color themes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for importing Jeskola BMX files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="walkthrough">
    <title>Walkthrough Guide</title>

    <para>The Aldrin walkthrough should give you a quick and helpful
    introduction into Aldrin. By the end of reading this chapter you will know
    how to install Aldrin, load generators and effects, write patterns and
    arrange those patterns in a sequence.</para>

    <sect1 id="installation">
      <title>Installation</title>

      <para>Aldrin is open source and therefore its releases are source code
      only - no binaries. If you use a popular distribution of GNU/Linux,
      chances are that your local package manager already offers an Aldrin
      package. If not, you will need to build Aldrin yourself.</para>

      <para>Independent of which distribution you use, building and installing
      Aldrin shouldn't be hard, given that you follow this guide. If you have
      trouble installing Aldrin, please contact your distribution maintainers
      and ask them to include support for Aldrin.</para>

      <para>First make sure that you have all programs and libraries installed
      required to build Aldrin. Usually, all of them should be provided by
      your distribution of GNU/Linux. Please check with your distributions
      package manager documentation on how to search and install packages. You
      are going to need following packages:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.python.org/">Python 2.4</ulink> or
          later.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.wxpython.org/">wxPython 2.6</ulink> or
          later, although 2.6 is recommended.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://python.net/crew/theller/ctypes/">ctypes</ulink>,
          if you are using Python 2.4. Since Python 2.5, ctypes is
          included.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.scons.org/">SCons 0.96.92</ulink> or
          later.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://trac.zeitherrschaft.org/zzub/">pyzzub
          0.2.2</ulink> or later. pyzzub is a specialized component based on
          libzzub that your distribution is most likely not supplying. Please
          see the installation guide for libzzub for details.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Aldrin packages can be downloaded from the SourceForge.net <ulink
      url="http://aldrin.sf.net">project website</ulink>. You can either
      download a release or build Aldrin from the source repository. In this
      guide, we are going to download a release.</para>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>On the project website, click on
          <guilabel>Downloads</guilabel> to see available releases. You will
          see the downloads page on which one or more releases are
          listed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Download the sources of the most recent release. Usually, the
          link should be named something like Aldrin <replaceable>x.x Source
          Release (x86, .tar.bz2)</replaceable>, where x.x is the release
          number.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Unpack the downloaded sources into a new folder. You will get
          a new subfolder named something like
          <replaceable>aldrin-x.x</replaceable>:</para>

          <screen><prompt>[paniq@aspera tmp]$</prompt><command> tar -vxf <replaceable>aldrin-x.x.tar.bz2</replaceable></command>
...
aldrin-x.x/CREDITS
aldrin-x.x/INSTALL
aldrin-x.x/ChangeLog
aldrin-x.x/LICENCE</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Change into the newly created folder and run scons to see if
          everything is fine:</para>

          <screen><prompt>[paniq@aspera tmp]$</prompt> <command>cd <replaceable>aldrin-x.x</replaceable></command><prompt>
[paniq@aspera aldrin-x.x]$</prompt> <command>scons</command>
scons: Reading SConscript files ...
scons: done reading SConscript files.
scons: Building targets ...
scons: `.' is up to date.
scons: done building targets.</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
		<para>Please make sure that any previous versions of Aldrin have been uninstalled from your system before proceeding with the next step.</para>
          <para>Now install aldrin to your system (you will need root rights
          for this):</para>

          <screen><prompt>[paniq@aspera aldrin-x.x]$</prompt> <command>sudo scons install</command>
Password:
scons: Reading SConscript files ...
scons: done reading SConscript files.
scons: Building targets ...
Install file: "bin/aldrin" as "/usr/local/bin/aldrin"
...
scons: done building targets.</screen>

          <para>If you don't want to install aldrin systemwide, create a
          folder in your home directory and change your installation
          prefix:</para>

          <screen><prompt>[paniq@aspera aldrin-x.x]$</prompt> <command>mkdir <replaceable>~/usr</replaceable></command>
<prompt>[paniq@aspera aldrin-x.x]$</prompt> <command>scons install PREFIX=<replaceable>/home/paniq/usr</replaceable></command>
scons: Reading SConscript files ...
scons: done reading SConscript files.
scons: Building targets ...
Install file: "bin/aldrin" as "/home/paniq/usr/bin/aldrin"
...
scons: done building targets.</screen>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>You are now ready to run Aldrin for the first time.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="running">
      <title>Running Aldrin</title>

      <para>If you installed Aldrin systemwide, you can find Aldrin in your
      desktop environments start menu in the section <guimenu>Sound &amp;
      Video</guimenu>.</para>

      <para>If you installed Aldrin into your homefolder, you have to run it
      manually. In the previous example, we installed Aldrin to
      <replaceable>/home/paniq/usr</replaceable>, which means that the
      applications start script <command>aldrin</command> will reside in
      <replaceable>/home/paniq/usr/bin</replaceable>. Run that script.</para>

      <para>You will be greeted by a splash screen that fades when Aldrin has
      been fully initialized. During startup, Aldrin will guess the best sound
      driver available and run it. If there was a problem during
      initialization of the sound device, you will be notified of the problem
      and asked to pick a different configuration in the Preferences
      dialog.</para>

      <para>Pretend that everything has worked correctly. Your startup screen
      should be looking like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Aldrin main window after first start.</title>

        <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_startview.png" scale="30" />
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="configure">
      <title>Configuring Aldrin</title>

      <para>Most likely, you will want to configure Aldrin a bit before you
      get started. If it hasn't opened automatically, open the preferences by
      selecting <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>View</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the menu. The preferences dialog will reveal itself to you:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Aldrin preferences window (Audio tab).</title>

        <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_preferences_wave.png" scale="30" />
      </figure>

      <para>The <guibutton>Audio</guibutton> tab is usually selected by
      default. It allows you to change settings related to audio output.
      Following explanation of parameters should you give a better understanding on what to choose.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Device</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The output device you wish to use. This usually lists JACK
            (if enabled), ALSA and OSS output drivers available on your
            system. All of these drivers require exclusive access to the
            soundcard for performance reasons, so make sure you have no other
            sound applications active in the background. I recommend ALSA to be tried first, then JACK, then OSS.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Samplerate</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The samplerate at which to render audio in Hz (impulses per
            second). 44100Hz is usually a good setting (CD Quality). The
            higher your samplerate is, the more performance Aldrin consumes to
            render sound. With a lower samplerate, Aldrin consumes less CPU
            time, but the sound quality is degraded.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Latency</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The time between the rendering of a signal and the actual
            output on the soundcard. Latency controls the size of the internal
            audio buffer that data is being rendered into before it is sent to
            the soundcard. A low latency value will give you a better response
            time, while a higher latency value gives you better
            performance. A value of 5-10ms should be acceptable.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Once you have set up your favorite settings, hit
      <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to test your new settings. If everything
      works correctly, move over to the <guibutton>Sound Library</guibutton>
      tab:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Aldrin preferences window (Sound Library tab).</title>

        <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_preferences_wt.png" scale="30" />
      </figure>

      <para>The <interface>Sound Library</interface> window allows you to manage a
      list of sample repositories. In order to access samples on your
      harddrive, you should at least add one sample repository. Click on
      <guibutton>Add...</guibutton>, then choose a folder to add.</para>
	  
	  <para>If you want to download samples online from within Aldrin, you need
	  to supply your freesound credentials. If you don't have a freesound account
	  yet, visit the website and get yourself one.</para>

      <para>If you are using external MIDI gear, you should have a look at the
      <guibutton>MIDI</guibutton> and <guibutton>Controllers</guibutton>
      tabs. They allow you to select MIDI input/output devices and configure MIDI controller bindings.</para>

      <!-- XXX: describe midi tabs -->

      <para>Aldrin allows you to use your keyboard like a 2-octave piano.
      Depending which keymap you use, you need to select a proper keymap on
      the <guibutton>Keyboard</guibutton> tab:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Aldrin preferences window (Keyboard tab).</title>

        <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_preferences_kb.png" scale="30" />
      </figure>

      <para>These are the most important settings. Once you are done
      adjusting, hit <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to apply your preferences and
      close the preferences window.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="makingnoise">
      <title>Making Some Noise</title>

      <para>Now that Aldrin is set up, you are ready to create a very small
      song, consisting of one plugin, one pattern and one sequence. This is a
      repeating process for every new song, and every new instrument you
      introduce.</para>

      <sect2 id="addingplugin">
        <title>Right Where It Belongs: Routing Plugins</title>

        <para>You should now be back where you begun:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>The router view.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_startview.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>

        <para>What you are seeing is the <interface>Router View</interface> of
        Aldrin. It allows you to chain generators and effects to define a
        processing order of signals. What does that mean? Let's try an
        example.</para>

        <para>Right-click somewhere in the empty space of the view. You should
        see the routers context menu. Select <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem>Makk M4wII</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>. A new generator plugin will appear at the coordinates where you
        right-clicked the view:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>A new plugin.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_newplugin.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>

        <para>The Makk M4wII is a quite feature-rich synthesizer, imitating an
        analogue synth model. Right now, the M4wII is not connected to the
        master output, and thus you will not be able to hear anything. Connect
        the synth to the master by clicking the plugin with the
        <mousebutton>middle</mousebutton> mouse button, and dragging the
        appearing arrow to the master plugin. You can also connect machines by
        holding <keycap>Shift</keycap> and using the
        <mousebutton>left</mousebutton> mouse button.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>A router connection.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_connection.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="createpattern">
        <title>The Core of Composition: Editing Patterns</title>

        <para>Now that the synth is created, hit the <keycap>F2</keycap> key
        to show the <interface>Pattern View</interface>.When you create a
        generator, Aldrin automatically adds a first empty pattern for you to
        work on, so you should now see the empty pattern:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>The pattern view.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_pattern.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>

        <para>In this pattern, time flows vertically, while actual changes in
        parameters are arranged horizontally. When a parameter does not
        change, it's associated column only shows one or more dots. You can
        click on fields or use the arrows on your keyboard to navigate in the
        pattern. For each column, the status bar will display the row index,
        the column index, the current value, it's readable representation, if
        any, and a long description of the parameter.</para>

        <para>It is possible that you can not see the entire pattern width, so
        you need to move to the first track. Hit <keycap>Tab</keycap> to jump
        to the first track, then use the keyboard to enter a few notes into
        the first column named <guilabel>Note</guilabel>:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>A pattern track with a few notes entered.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_patterntrack.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>

        <para>As you enter each note, M4wII will be triggered to play that
        note, allowing you to preview what you are writing. The cursor
        travels down by one row. You can change the pattern
        length and name either by selecting <guimenuitem>Pattern
        Properties...</guimenuitem> from the pattern views context menu, or
        using the keyboard shortcut <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>Backspace</keycap>
          </keycombo>.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Pattern properties.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_patternprops.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Name</guilabel></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The name of the pattern. Aldrin usually enumerates
              patterns with a sequence like 00, 01, 02, and so on, but you are
              free to choose your own names.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Length</guilabel></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The length of the pattern in rows (= ticks). You can see
              from the <guilabel>TPB</guilabel> edit field at the top of the
              main window that the song is currently set up to 4 "ticks per
              beats", which is the number of rows that is being played per
              beat. One bar consists of four beats, so that's 4x4 rows = 16
              rows - precisely the number of rows that your pattern has right
              now. The dropdown box provides you with a set of defaults for
              different speed and bar settings.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="createsequence">
        <title>Putting It All Together: Sequences</title>

        <para>Once your pattern contains some notes, you will want to put your
        pattern into your songs sequence. In order to do that, hit
        <keycap>F4</keycap> to enter the <interface>Sequence View</interface>.
        You will see a screen that looks like this:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sequencer View.</title>

          <graphic fileref="../images/aldrin_sequencer.png" scale="30" />
        </figure>

        <para>Since you created a generator, the sequence view already
        contains a track for the M4wII, but it is currently empty. By moving
        left and right with the <keycap>arrow keys</keycap> on your keyboard, you
        can change the time index. Moving up and down will change the track and plugin
		you are adding patterns for. On the right side of the window, there is a <interface>Pattern
        List</interface>, which lists the available patterns you can put into
        that track. Each pattern is prefixed by the name of the key that you
        should press on the keyboard to place that pattern into the sequence.
        In our example, pressing <keycap>0</keycap> will put pattern 00 in the
        current track at the current time index your cursor is at.</para>

        <para>Now hit <keycap>F5</keycap> to listen to what your song sounds
        like. <keycap>F8</keycap> will stop the song. Your first track -
        although a bit bland and simple - is finished!</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Keyboard Shortcuts Reference</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>Universal Shortcuts</title>

      <para>These keyboard shortcuts can be triggered from all locations in
      the application.</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F2</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to <interface>Pattern View</interface>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F3</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to <interface>Router View</interface>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F4</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to <interface>Sequence View</interface>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F5</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Play song from beginning of song or loop.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F6</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Play song from current cursor position in sequencer.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F7</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Enable/Disable automation.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F8</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Stop song and plugins.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F9</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Show <interface>Sound Library</interface>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F10</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Show <interface>Info View</interface>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>F12</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Enable/disable audio driver.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist> 

    </sect1>
	
    <sect1>
      <title>Pattern View Shortcuts</title>

      <para>These keyboard shortcuts can be triggered from within the Pattern view.</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>A</keycap>-<keycap>Z</keycap>/<keycap>0</keycap>-<keycap>9</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert note/value and advance one row.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Arrow Keys</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Change column/row.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Arrow Up</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Arrow Down</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to previous/next plugin.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Page Up</keycap>/<keycap>Page Down</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Move 16 rows back/forward.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Home</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Move to begin of track/tracks/global group/row.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Insert</keycap>/<keycap>Delete</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert/delete one row.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Return</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to <interface>Sequence View</interface>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Return</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Create new pattern.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Return</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Copy current pattern.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Numpad +</keycap>/<keycap>Numpad -</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to next/previous pattern of plugin.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Numpad +</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Numpad -</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Transpose selection up/down.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Numpad +</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Numpad -</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Add new/delete last track.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Numpad *</keycap>/<keycap>Numpad %</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Increase/decrease current base octave.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Tab</keycap>/<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Move to next/previous track.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>BackSpace</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Show <interface>Pattern Properties</interface> dialog.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Delete</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Delete current pattern.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>1</keycap></keycombo>-<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>9</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Change current stepsize to 1-9 steps.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Mark begin/end of current column/track/group/all (press multiple to select).</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Copy current selection to clipboard.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Paste to cursor position from clipboard.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>X</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Cut current selection and copy to clipboard.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Randomize current selection.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>I</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Interpolate current selection.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>U</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Reset selection.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Solo current plugin.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist> 

    </sect1>
	
    <sect1>
      <title>Sequence View Shortcuts</title>

      <para>These keyboard shortcuts can be triggered from within the Sequence View.</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>0</keycap>-<keycap>9</keycap>/<keycap>A</keycap>-<keycap>Z</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert associated pattern and advance by pattern size.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Space</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert currently highlighted pattern in pattern list at cursor and advance by pattern size.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>.</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Clear pattern at cursor position.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>-</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert <command>Mute</command> command at cursor position and advance by step size.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>,</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert <command>Break</command> command at cursor position and advance by step size.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Arrow Keys</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Change plugin/time index.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Arrow Left</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Arrow Right</keycap></keycombo>
				<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Numpad +</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Numpad -</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Increase/decrease time step size.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Arrow Left</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Arrow Right</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Move cursor 16 steps back/forward.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Arrow Up</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Arrow Down</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch current track with previous/next track.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select previous/next pattern in pattern list.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Insert</keycap>/<keycap>Delete</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert/delete one time index step at the current cursor position.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Delete</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Delete current track.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycap>Return</keycap>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Switch to <interface>Pattern View</interface> and show the pattern under the cursor.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Return</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Open <interface>Parameter View</interface> for the current plugin.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>/<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Set begin/end of loop. Setting end of loop twice sets end of song as well.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Copy current selection to clipboard.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Paste to cursor position from clipboard.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>X</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Cut current selection and copy to clipboard.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>I</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Insert new time index step on all tracks.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>Solo current plugin.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist> 

    </sect1>

  </chapter>
</book>