<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="lunar_lfo">
  <title>Lunar LFO</title>
  <para>
    Use Lunar LFO to control parameters of other machines (including
    other Lunar LFO instances). This is useful for adding movement to
    sound when a particular machine does not provide an LFO modulation
    option for some parameter. This LFO synchronizes with the song
    position, which means that the song will sound the same each
    time, no matter where or when you start the playback. This machine
    also comes with its' own GUI. This GUI allows you to visualize LFO
    wave shape and the range of values it cycles through.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Lunar LFO Screenshot</title>
    <graphic fileref="images/lunar_lfo.png"></graphic>
  </figure>
  <para>
    Lunar LFO screenshot is presented in the figure. The green line
    represents the LFO wave shape. Drag the gray bars with the mouse
    up or down to adjust the range which the LFO output can take. The
    red bar represents where in the LFO wave the playback cursor is
    at. The sliders are used to adjust offset and rate
    respectively. These parameters are explained in the table
    below. If you click on the LFO wave visualization with your left
    mouse button it will move forward by one wave shape, if you click
    with the right button it will move backward one shape. The "Drag to
    connect button" should be self explanatory. If it is not - you
    should try clicking on it and then dragging and dropping on a
    slider you want to control.
  </para>
  <table><title>Lunar LFO Parameters</title>
  <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
    <thead>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Parameter</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Meaning</para></entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Wave</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Pick an LFO wave to use. You can see its' shape in the GUI
	  so those are not listed here.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Offset</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  This value will be added to the playback position when
	  calculating how far in to the LFO wave the cursor should
	  be.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Rate</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  How fast (in rows) should an LFO cycle complete. That is, if
	  the value is, say, 64, it will take it one pattern of length
	  64 to finish. If you want the cycle to start exactly at the
	  start of the pattern you might need to use the offset
	  parameter.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Min</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  The relative minimum of the LFO output range. That is, if
	  the machine parameter you want to control goes, say, from 0
	  to 100 and the Min is set to 0.1 and the Max is set to 0.6,
	  then the parameter will cycle from 10 to 60 while the LFO
	  completes one round of its' eternal journey.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Max</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Mins' brother.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>
</section>
