<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="mdaLeslie">
  <title>mda Leslie</title>
  <para>
    A port of mda's Leslie Rotary Speaker simulator.
  </para>
  <para>
    A Leslie speaker is a special amplifier and set of speakers mounted in such a way that the rotation of the components creates a pleasing
    doppler effect.  It's something like a very wide chorus and phaser.  There is a crossover circuit so the exact parameters of the sound
    can be controlled independently for high and low tones.
  </para>
  <para>
    This sound is especially suited to electric pianos and (Hammond) organs.
  </para>
  <table><title>Parameters</title>
  <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
    <thead>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Parameter</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Meaning</para></entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Speed</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        Overall operation speed.  Can be one of 'STOP' (no rotation), 'SLOW' or 'FAST'.  Param 'Finespeed' futher allows you to tweak actual speed to suit.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Gain</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        Output gain.  Use to give signal a boost if operation attenuates signal a little.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Crossover</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        Crossover frequency between hi and low speakers.  Moving this up can result in a more disorientating sound.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>High Width</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        High tone speaker (tweeter) stereo modulation width.  Makes the sound wobble from side to side more!
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>High Depth</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        High tone speaker phase shift size.  Sort of simulates the sound receding and approaching.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>High Throb</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        High tone speaker volume modulation.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Low Width</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        As for high width, but for low tones from the woofer.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Fine speed</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        Fine control over rotation speed.  Can take a few seconds to reach the desired speed, to simulate
        the momentum of a real Leslie speaker!
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Low Throb</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
        Again, as for high throb but for low tones.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>
<para>
    Ported by mrmonkington https://bitbucket.org/mrmonkington/neil
</para>
</section>
