<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="pattern_view">
  <title>Pattern view</title>
  <section>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>Use this view to enter pattern data. Since Neil is a so-called
    tracker, you have to enter notes in a certain quite peculiar
    format. Time in trackers go from top to bottom. Each line in this
    view is a musical event. Columns are used to enter data which are
    always integral numbers displayed in hexadecimal. These numbers can
    be used to set synthesizer parameters, note values and other
    performance data.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Editting patterns</title>
    <para>
      An example of a 16 bar pattern is shown bellow. It is for the
      Oomek Aggressor machine. Oomek Aggressor is a an emulator of a
      famous bassline synthesizer by a famous Japanese company. It
      comes with the standard Neil machine set and it has very many
      musical applications starting with obvious basslines and acid
      leads and ending with sound effects and all even pads. If you
      need examples of good use for this kind of synthesizer just
      check out old Plastikman records. To see how you add this
      machine to your song read the manual page on using the Router
      view. This assumes that you have added the machine and have the
      first pattern open in the pattern editor. Obviously, when you
      open that view it won't contain the pattern below. This is just
      a pattern I entered semi-randomly.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
0 6E 5A 6E 64 2C 64 32 | D#5 . 1
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | C#4 1 .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | D#4 1 .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | D#3 1 .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | D#4 . 1
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | F-5 . .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | F-5 1 .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | F-3 . .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | D#5 . 1
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | C-5 1 .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | F#3 . .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | D#5 . .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | F#5 1 1
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | E-5 . .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | A#5 . .
. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. | B-4 . .
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      You can see that the view is divided in to two big columns. The
      first one contains global parameters and the other one contains
      track parameters. A particular machine can ommit one or both of
      these. Global parameters usually control the sound of the
      synth. It is used to enter values that would affect, for example,
      cutoff frequency of a synthesizers filter. As a matter of fact
      this one does contain a column for that. You use the arrow keys to
      move around in the pattern view editor. Click with the mouse on
      the view if it is not in focus and try using the arrow keys to
      move the cursor. As you move the cursor notice that a short
      description of the column you are on appears below the pattern
      editor. For example, try locating the cutoff frequency and
      resonance in the global parameter column.
    </para>
    <para>
      Values are entered using a hexadecimal base format. This used to
      be done because it allows to enter values that fit in to one
      byte using just two digits. Similarly it allows to enter two
      bytes using four digits. It has to do with the way that
      computers store information. While it requires to think a little
      differently it is a compact way of entering numeric information
      in to computers. To convert from hexadecimal to decimal you can
      use the two formulas below. They are for the two and four digit
      cases respectively. Neil only allows those two types of numeric
      values. 
    </para>
    <section><title>Convert from Hexadecimal</title>
    <para>
      Equation for two digit numbers (that go up to 255) is below. The
      number before the equality sign is a hexadecimal number. It
      consists of two digits in hexadecimal format. Digits up to ten
      are displayed as usual, while the numbers higher than ten are as
      follows: a := 10, b := 11, c := 12, d := 13, e := 14, f :=
      15. As you can see, one hexadecimal digit can represent numbers
      from zero to fifteen. If you have, for example, hexadecimal
      number 2e, you can convert it to decimal by doing the following
      simple calculation
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>(2e)<subscript>x</subscript> = (16 *
      2 + 14)<subscript>d</subscript> =
      (46)<subscript>d</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>.
    </para>
    <equation><title>Two digit case</title>
      <mathphrase>
	(xy)<subscript>x</subscript> = (16x + y)<subscript>d</subscript>
      </mathphrase>
    </equation>
    <para>
      Converting four digit columns is outlined in the equation
      below. It works analogously to the two digit case.
    </para>
    <equation><title>Four digit case</title>
	<mathphrase>
	  (wxyz)<subscript>x</subscript> = (16<superscript>3</superscript>w + 16<superscript>2</superscript>x + 16y + z)<subscript>d</subscript>
	</mathphrase>
    </equation>
    </section>
    <section><title>Converting to Hexadecimal</title>
    <para>
      Converting decimal values to hexadecimal ones is a bit more
      involved than the other way round. To convert them you need to
      use integer division and modulo operators. They will be written
      / and % respectively. The first operator simply divides an
      integer by another integer and drops the remainder. The other
      one divides one integer by another and returns the
      remainder. So, for example 5 / 2 = 2, while 5 % 2 = 1.
    </para>
    <para>
      We need to consider two cases. The first one is the two digit
      columns, while the second one is four digit columns. When two
      digits are used, the highest decimal number that can be
      expressed is 255 (or ff in hexadecimal). If four digits are
      used, the highest number that can be expressed is 65535 (or ffff
      in hexadecimal). We will show how to convert numbers that are
      below 255 and below 65535 separately.
    </para>
    <para>
      To convert a number x, where x &lt; 255 to a decimal number y
      that consists of two digits:
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>y<subscript>1</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>
      and
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>y<subscript>2</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>, you
      get those digits use the two formulas below.
    </para>
    <equation><title>First Digit</title>
    <mathphrase>
      y<subscript>1</subscript> = x / 16
    </mathphrase>
    </equation>
    <equation><title>Second Digit</title>
    <mathphrase>
      y<subscript>2</subscript> = x % 16
    </mathphrase>
    </equation>
    <para>
      To convert a number x where x &lt; 65535 to a decimal number y
      that consists of four digits:
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>y<subscript>1</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>, 
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>y<subscript>2</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>, 
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>y<subscript>3</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation> and 
      <inlineequation><mathphrase>y<subscript>4</subscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>,
      you get those digits using the formulas below.
    </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Navigating with keyboard</title>
    <para>
      For those of you who prefer using keyboard to using mouse (this
      is probably everyone when shown how). Apart from moving the
      cursor with arrow keys there are ways to change the active
      machine, pattern, wave, step, octave and to make selections in
      the pattern editor. To change the active machine use Ctrl + Up
      and Ctrl + Down shortcut. To change the active pattern use "+"
      and "-" keys on the numeric keypad if your are on a laptop use
      the key kombination that emulates numeric keypad. Plus key
      increases active pattern number while the minus key decreases
      it. To change the active wave you can use the "&#60;" and
      "&#62;" keys. Use the "*" and "/" keys on the numpad to change
      the active octave up and down one octave. Use the "[" and "]"
      keys to change the step size for the editor. To manage
      selections with the keyboard just hold down the "Shift" button
      and use the arrow keys to select. When you want to deselect,
      release the "Shift" key and use the arrow keys to move the
      cursor. 
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Shortcuts</title>
    <table><title>Pattern View Shortcuts</title>
    <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
	<row>
	  <entry><para>Shortcut</para></entry>
	  <entry><para>Action</para></entry>
	</row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+Shift+Enter</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Create a copy of the currently open pattern.</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+Enter</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Create a new pattern</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+Backspace</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Display pattern properties</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+Delete</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Delete current pattern</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Shift+Plus</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Transpose the note at cursor by +1</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Shift+Minus</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Transpose the note at cursor by -1</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+c</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Copy selection to clipboard</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+x</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Cut selection to clipboard</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+v</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Paste from clipboard</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+i</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Interpolate selection</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+Plus</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Add a track</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Ctrl+Minus</para>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <para>Delete last track</para>
	  </entry>
	</row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
</section>
