<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="somono_cloud">
  <title>SoMono Cloud</title>
  <para>
    Cloud is a grain synthesis based synthesizer. It takes a wave file and
    plays back short parts of it with varying parameters that are chosen
    at random from a given range. Each such short part is called a
    grain. You can select it's length, starting offset into the wave file,
    envelope parameters, rate, etc. You can specify the probability for
    playback during each processing cycle (currently 256 samples).
  </para>
  <para>
    When loading stereo files Cloud will only load the first channel. If
    the wave file is longer than 10 seconds only the first 10 seconds
    will be used. The first limitation is an implementation choice that
    results in a simpler program while the second one is because the
    wave data needs to be loaded in to computer memory. They should not
    interfere to much with the usual use cases of granular synthesizers.
  </para>
  <table><title>SoMono Cloud Parameters</title>
  <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
    <thead>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Parameter</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Meaning</para></entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Wave</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  This allows you to pick a loaded wave file from a wave slot by name. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Offset Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  The mean offset into the wave file. This is the percentage by
	  which the playback is skipped in to the wave file. For example setting
	  this to 50% will start the playback from the middle of the file for
	  each new grain.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Offset Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  This and other devi (deviation) parameters let you adjust how
	  much will the actual value deviate randomly from the mean value that
	  you set using the mean parameters. For example if offset mean value
	  ranges from 0% to 100% then setting Offset Devi parameter to say 0.1
	  and setting Offset Mean to say 50% then the actual value will be from
	  the interval (40%, 60%) picked at random. This works the same way for
	  all the other parameters.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Amp Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Each grains output is multiplied by the value specified by this
	  parameter thus scaling the volume down if it is set to something less
	  than 1. You use it to either avoid clipping when alot of grains are
	  playing at the same time or with the devi parameter to allow grains of
	  different volumes.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Amp Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Deviation value for the amp parameter. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Length Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  The length for which each grain will be playing in miliseconds. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Length Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Deviation value for the length parameter. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Sustain Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  This value stands for the percentage of time (which was
	  specified with the length parameter) that wil be spent in the sustain
	  stage.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Sustain Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Deviation value for the sustain parameter. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Skew Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Skew in this case means the amount of playback time that will be
	  spent in the attack stage. If skew is set to 50% than it means that
	  both attack and decay stages will be given equal time. If it is set to
	  20% it means that attack will be given 20% of the time that is left
	  after accounting for sustain and release will be given the remaining
	  80% thus attack will be shorter than release. You get the picture.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Skew Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Deviation value for the skew parameter. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Rate Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Playback rate for each grain. Value 0.0 means that each grain plays
	  at the original rate, 1.0 means that the it is played twice as fast,
	  -1.0 that it is played twice as slow etc.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Rate Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Deviation value for the rate parameter. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Pan Mean</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  The panorama position of the grain. Here -1.0 means panning hard
	  left and 1.0 means panning hard right, the other values cover the rest
	  of the panorama spectrum.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Pan Devi</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Deviation value for the pan parameter. 
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Density</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  Probability that a grain will be triggered for playback at each
	  given processing cycle. The bigger this value the more grains playing
	  at the same time.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
	<entry><para>Grains</para></entry>
	<entry><para>
	  The maximum number of grains that can be playing that the same
	  time.
	</para></entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>
</section>
